<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A serious inquiry into the means of an happy union, or, What reformation is necessary to prevent popery and to avert God's judgments from the nation written upon the occasion of the fast, and humbly offered to the consideration of the Parliament by William Saywell.</title>
            <author>Saywell, William, 1643-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25119</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08770253</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08770253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1268:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A serious inquiry into the means of an happy union, or, What reformation is necessary to prevent popery and to avert God's judgments from the nation written upon the occasion of the fast, and humbly offered to the consideration of the Parliament by William Saywell.</title>
                  <author>Saywell, William, 1643-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.G. and J.P., and are to be sold by Rand. Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Serious Inquiry Into the Means of an HAPPY UNION: OR, What Reformation is Neceſſary to prevent Popery, and to avert God's Judgments from the Nation.</p>
            <p>Written upon the occaſion of the FAST, and humbiy offered to the Conſideration OF THE PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SAYWELL, <hi>D. D. Maſter of Jeſus College in Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. G.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Rand. Taylor</hi> near Stationers Hall. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41764:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41764:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Serious Inquiry</hi> Into the means of an Happy Union:</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU having made an Addreſs to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to proclaim a Publick Faſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Nation, all good men ought to hope your intentions are in a Chriſtian way to appeaſe Gods anger that has been kindled againſt us, and to purſue ſuch Methods as may prevent thoſe heavy Judgments that hang over our heads; and therefore I may preſume that you will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily embrace any Propoſals that ſhall be offered you out of Gods Word, to ſhew the Cauſes and Remedies of our Diſtractions.</p>
               <p>Two things generally are deſigned in ſuch Faſts: 1. An Humiliation under the Sins that have been the cauſe of thoſe Judgments under which we groan.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41764:3"/>2. A Supplication for Direction and Aſſiſtance to find out and purſue thoſe means and ways which will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Puniſhments that God does threaten us withall.</p>
               <p>That 'tis Sin that does bring confuſion and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a People, is plain by the threatnings and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, that we read of throughout the Old Teſtament, where are innumerable inſtances of Gods ſevere puniſhments inflicted upon his own People, for their tranſgreſſing of his Commandments; and S. <hi>Paul</hi> does tell us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Theſe things were our examples, to the intent we ſhould not luſt after evil things, as they alſo luſted. And they are written for our admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ver.</hi> 11. That by avoiding the ſin we may alſo eſcape the puniſhment. But I need not prove this, ſince your deſiring of a Faſt is an acknowledgment of your belief thereof.</p>
               <p>The next thing will be to inquire what ſins they are for which God does thus ſhew his indignation againſt us. Now in reckoning up theſe ſins every Party will follow their own inclinations, and be ſure to acquit themſelves, and lay all the blame upon their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Thus a Papiſt will ſay, all theſe miſchiefs come upon us, becauſe we have forſaken the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church. The Presbyterians and Independents, becauſe by enacting the Obſervation of Ceremonies, and requiring Declarations and Subſcriptions which they will not take, we have ſilenced ſo many Godly Miniſters, and ſcandalized other ſerious Chriſtians. An Anabaptiſt and a Quaker will ſay, it comes for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the People of God. Others again will ſay, and with more reaſon, that God is angry with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for that general Contempt of his Commandments,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41764:3"/>whether it be in open profaneneſs and neglect of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or elſe in the licentious profeſſion of an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Faith and Worſhip, to the great diſtracting of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſober and well meaning People. That I may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtate the whole matter, I will reduce the publick ſins of the Nation to four heads, which I ſuppoſe will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the chiefeſt things whereby God is provoked to ſhew his diſpleaſure againſt us; theſe are <hi>Hereſie, Schiſm, Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi> Hereſie, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one or more neceſſary Truths of the Goſpel; Schiſm, in breaking the Unity of Chriſts Body; Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in not taking pains to come to the Knowledge of Truth; and Profaneneſs, in acting contrary to their Knowledge and Profeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THat Hereſie is a crying ſin,<note place="margin">Hereſie and Schiſm damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſins.</note> that will bring Gods Judgments upon a People where it is publickly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, is plain, becauſe it is a ſin that God has threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with damnation. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. amongſt other ſins Hereſies are reckoned, and of them all 'tis ſaid, <hi>They that do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God Titus</hi> 3.10. <hi>A man that is an Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject; knowing that ſuch a one is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelf.</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers, who ſhall privily bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction.</hi> We are further taught wherein this Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie doth conſiſt, 2 <hi>John ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Whoſoever tranſgreſſeth,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41764:4"/>and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God.</hi> And 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7, 8, 9. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven, with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction.</hi> So that not onely ſinning againſt the natural light of Conſcience, or that Religion and Perſuaſion that a man is convinced of, but tranſgreſſing the known Doctrine of Chriſt, and diſobeying the Goſpel, is a damnable ſin, and the publick permiſſion thereof will bring deſtruction to a Nation.</p>
               <p>Schiſm,<note place="margin">Schiſm a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſin.</note> that is another damning ſin, and the open allowance of it muſt bring Judgment upon a Nation. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. where the word is rendered <hi>Seditions,</hi> it does as properly ſignifie <hi>Schiſms</hi> alſo, and then of them 'tis ſaid, <hi>They which do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Mark thoſe which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them; for they that are ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies; and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> And S. <hi>Jude</hi> tells us of thoſe that under the Goſpel <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the gainſaying of Core.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jude v. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> And that we may know what ſort of men they are, he adds <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Theſe be they which ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not go about to prove that Ignorance of the Goſpel and Profaneneſs are damning ſins,<note place="margin">Ignorance and Profaneneſs damnable ſins.</note> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently will bring Gods Judgments upon the Nation. Now all theſe four ſins follow one from another; the firſt is Hereſie or Falſe Perſuaſion, contrary to the truth of the Goſpel; that as it is damnable alone, ſo it will lead men into Schiſms and Diviſions, and they will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41764:4"/>make men negligent and careleſs, and that will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily keep them in ignorance, and make them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get both God and their duty; and then the next ſtep is to Profaneneſs. So that to keep out Profaneneſs we muſt baniſh Ignorance, and to prevent Ignorance we muſt quiet Schiſms and Diſtractions, and to ſilence them we muſt take away Hereſies and Falſe Opinions, by inſtructing men in ſober knowledge of the Truth, and keeping out all Heretical and Schiſmatical Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. The firſt thing then to be ſet about in order to appeaſe Gods anger, is to eſtabliſh ſound and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and prevent the ſpreading of Hereſie and Falſe Doctrine, which will unavoidably bring Schiſm, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and Profaneneſs. For 'tis a certain truth, that ignorant and profane perſons do and will ſhelter themſelves under the pretence of being Diſſenters, and the multitude of Diviſions does make careleſs people believe there is no ſuch thing as Religion at all; which is too too evident by the prodigious growth of Atheiſm and Irreligion, ever ſince theſe Diviſions have been countenanced in 41, under the colour of being favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Tender Conſciences, and indulging to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sober Proteſtants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41764:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HEreſie and Schiſm being in themſelves crying ſins, and the cauſes of Ignorance and Profaneneſs, we muſt ſee in the next place upon whom the charge of theſe Crimes muſt be laid, that ſo we may find out the true means to redreſs them.</p>
               <p>And firſt becauſe the word <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is ſo much uſed in the ſtyle of our times,<note place="margin">Anabaptists and Quakers Hereticks.</note> I will begin with the ſenſe of the Proteſtant Churches abroad, concerning ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies that are preached, and openly maintained by many that are now called Sober Proteſtants. And firſt I will begin with Baptiſm, which is wholly laid aſide by the Quakers, and denied to all Infants as unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the Anabaptiſts, contrary to the expreſs Word of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</note> that ſays, <hi>Except any one be born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God;</hi> that is, either <hi>re</hi> or <hi>voto,</hi> when ordinary means are not to be had. Hence the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Confeſſion, of greateſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and moſt generally received in Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches beyond the Seas, ſays <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Of Baptiſm they teach, that it is neceſſary to Salvation as a Ceremony inſtituted by Chriſt: and that the grace of God is offered by Baptiſm: and that Infants are to be baptized: and that Infants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to God by Baptiſm are received into the favour of God, and are made the Children of God, as Chriſt does wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They do condemn the Anabaptiſts that reject Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Infants, and that do affirm that Infants may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without Baptiſm, and out of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The French Confeſſion, Art. 35. <hi>We acknowledge two Sacraments onely common to the whole Church, of which the firſt is Baptiſm, given us to teſtifie our Adoption, becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41764:5"/>by it we are engrafted into the Body of Chriſt, that being waſhed by his Bloud, we may alſo be renewed unto holineſs of life by his Spirit. Beſides, though Baptiſm be a Sacrament of faith and repentance, nevertheleſs ſince God does receive into his Church parents with their poſterity, we affirm that Infants that are born of holy parents are to be baptized by the authority of Chriſt. Acts</hi> 22.16 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>The Dutch Confeſſion, Art. 34. <hi>We believe that every man that deſires to attain eternal life, ought to be baptized with the one Baptiſm, that is, once onely. Neither doth this Baptiſm profit onely in that moment when the water re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains upon us, but throughout the whole time of our life. Therefore we deteſt here the error of the Anabaptiſts, who are not content with one onely Baptiſm once received, but alſo condemn the Baptiſm of Infants that are born of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful parents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Saxon Confeſſion, Art. 14. <hi>The Son of God ſitting at the right hand of his everlaſting Father is ſo efficatious in him, as S. Paul ſaith to the Galatians, As many as are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt. And he affirms the Holy Ghoſt is given in Baptiſm, when he ſaith in Titus, By the laver of regeneration, and the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt. And in John 'tis ſaid, Except any one be born again of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of Heaven. We teach therefore that Baptiſm is neceſſary, and we baptize none but once onely. We retain the Baptiſm of Infants, becauſe it is certain the promiſe of grace does alſo pertain unto Infants, and to them onely who are engrafted into the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we have ſeen what is the ſenſe of the Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Churches concerning theſe Anabaptiſts and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that either wholly ſet aſide Baptiſm as uſeleſs,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41764:6"/>or not neceſſary or at all belonging to Infants; let us inquire what was the Opinion of the Ancient and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church in this matter. That the practice of baptizing Infants was univerſal throughout all Ages of the Church, is clear from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> and all the Fathers in the following Ages. And when <hi>Pelagius</hi> denied the Doctrine of Original Sin, and the Neceſſity of Supernatural Grace, in that ſenſe which the Church had always received it, he did alſo deny the Neceſſity of Baptiſm for Infants; which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of his to the Catholick Truth cauſed ſeveral Councils to condemn his Hereſies, and was the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of S. <hi>Jeroms</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> and many other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers Writings, about this ſubject.</p>
               <p>Hence we have the Decree of the Council <hi>Milevis</hi> confirmed in the 77th. Canon of the <hi>African Codex; It pleaſeth us, that whoſoever he be that doth deny that little Children, that are newly born from their Mothers womb, ought to be baptized; or ſaith, that they are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for the remiſſion of ſins, but that they derive nothing of original ſin from Adam, that ought to be cleanſed by the laver of regeneration.</hi> From whence it does follow, <hi>That the Form of Baptiſm for the remiſſion of ſins is not underſtood to be true. but falſe and feigned, let him be an Anathema: becauſe that cannot be underſtood which was ſpoken by the Apoſtle, [By one man ſin came into the world, and death by ſin, and ſo death paſſed upon all foraſmuch as all have ſinned;] unleſs in that manner that it has been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Catholick Church every where ſpread abroad throughout the world. And becauſe of this rule of faith even Infants, who could commit no ſins in their own perſons, are truly baptized for the remiſſion of ſins,<note place="margin">Vide epiſt. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt. ad Epiſc. Gall.</note> that that may be cleanſed through regeneration, which they derived from their firſt generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41764:6"/>
               <p>Afterwards, the Acts that were paſt in condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Doctrine of <hi>Pelagius</hi> were ſent to the third General Council held at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and there confirmed by the univerſal Church, Act 5.<note place="margin">Relatio Conc. Eph. gen. <hi>3.</hi> ad Celeſt. act. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Commentaries of the things that were decreed and conſtituted by your Piety, in the depoſition of the wicked Pelagians and Celeſtians, of Celeſtius, Pelagius, Julianus, Perſidius, Florus, Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Orentius, and of thoſe that are of the ſame opinion with them, being read in the Synod, we have alſo judged that they ought to remain firm and valid, and we decree the ſame thing with you, and account them depoſed. And that you may be more certain of this, we have ſent you the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and the Subſcriptions of the Synod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were eaſie to prove the ſame more largly through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Chriſtian Church in all Ages ever ſince; ſo that the Quakers and Anabaptiſts being Hereticks by the Word of God, as it has been generally underſtood by Proteſtant Churches, and the Church Univerſal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their time, if they be openly tolerated to profeſs and propagate their Hereſie, it muſt needs bring down Gods Judgments upon our Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>NOW for Schiſm,<note place="margin">Papiſts, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, aend Independents Schiſmaticks, Numb. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> that is a ſin of that magnitude and heinous nature, that God did open the earth and ſwallow up men alive for it, and ſent a miraculous Fire to conſume the firſt Beginners of Schiſmatical Worſhip. And of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that worſhipped God in Schiſm our Lord ſays, <hi>Ye know not what ye worſhip.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 4.22.</note> Now this Schiſm was in oppoſing the lawful Officers which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41764:7"/>God had appointed to miniſter about holy things, and venturing upon the Sacred Function without any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly warrant to do it,</p>
               <p>And 'tis as plain a caſe that Chriſt has appinted Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Governours in his Church, and committed all the World to their Government in their reſpective Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, in things relating to his Worſhip. <hi>John</hi> 20. <hi>As my Father ſent me,</hi> (that is, to appoint Officers, and with Authority to rule and govern my Church all over the World) <hi>ſo ſend I you,</hi> (not <hi>Peter</hi> onely) to do the like. Again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>Go make diſciples in all nations; — and lo I am with you to the end of the world.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to every creature; he that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> So all the World were bound by the command of our Saviour to receive the Apoſtles, and ſuch as they ſent to preach the Goſpel, (for they could not ſpeak to all men perſonally) and be ruled by them according to the Goſpel, or elſe they were to be damned. Theſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles gave in charge alſo to the Biſhops and Paſtors, to rule and govern the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Over which the Holy Ghoſt had made them Biſhops.</hi> They are to <hi>exhort and rebuke with all authority; let no man deſpiſe them, Titus</hi> 2.15. They are to receive Accuſations and examine Witneſſes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. and therefore muſt have a Summoner to cite the Offender, and a Regiſter to write down the Informations and Depoſitions. They are to <hi>rebuke before all, that others may fear,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20. The People are commanded likewiſe to <hi>obey them that have the rule over them, and to ſubmit themſelves, for they watch for their ſouls, as they that muſt give account, Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>They are to know them that labour among them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41764:7"/>and are over them in the Lord, and admoniſh them; and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake;</hi> not for their Birth, or Parts, or natural Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but as Miniſters of Chriſt <hi>for their works ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. They are in caſe of offence given to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them with fear and trembling, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.15. And leſt any ſhould deſpiſe this Authority which our Lord has given, he has ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, whatſoever ye ſhall bind on earth ſhall be bound in heaven, and whatſoever ye ſhall looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 20.23. <hi>Whoſe ſoever ſins ye remit, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them; and whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is abundantly enough to demonſtrate, that Chriſt has appointed Governours in his Church, and commanded all men to obey them. And therefore to deſpiſe their Office, to contemn their Authority, and withdraw from their Communion, and to invade their Charges, is a crying ſin that will bring Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a Nation.</p>
               <p>But the Queſtion is ſtill, Who are the Governours that muſt be thus obeyed, and who are to ſend and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them? Now 'tis plain that this Authority is from Chriſt, and where he gave it he gave the Holy Ghoſt alſo with it; <hi>John</hi> 20. <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And 'tis plain, the Apoſtles having received the Holy Ghoſt, did convey it to other Paſtors, who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by them; <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>Govern the Church over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi> And When <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> told a Lie to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> he ſays,<note place="margin">Acts <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie againſt the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> So that thoſe that derive Authority in an orderly way by Succeſſion, from thoſe who have power given them to give the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41764:8"/>Holy Ghoſt for the work of a Biſhop,<note place="margin">Luther tom. <hi>2.</hi> ep. fol. <hi>41.</hi> Tu ex mea parte explores, an vocatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſuam poſſint probare. Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim Deus unquam aliquem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, niſi vel per hominem voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, vel per ſigna declaratum, ne ipſum quidem filium.</note> thoſe are ſuch Governours to whom we muſt yield obedience; and in oppoſing of them we ſhall oppoſe Chriſt. If any pretend to this Authority, and cannot ſhew they had it from them who were enabled to beſtow the Holy Ghoſt, they muſt ſhew miracles to prove it. For 'tis not Knowledge alone, or the Choice of the People, or the Appointment of the Magiſtrate, that can give the Holy Ghoſt, that muſt come from Chriſt, or ſome of thoſe that received that power by Succeſſion from him. And this is the Opinion of all Proteſtant Churches in their Confeſſions, (when it may be had) and has been the conſtant Tradition of the whole Church, and all the Catholick Writers in all Ages.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Confeſſion, Art. 14. <hi>Concerning the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Order we teach, that none ought publickly to teach or adminiſter the Sacraments, unleſs he be rightly called, as Paul does give in charge to Titus, that he ſhould appoint Elders in every City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Confeſſion, Art. 21. <hi>We believe that the true Church of Chriſt ought to be governed by that Polity or Diſcipline which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt eſtabliſhed, that there ſhould be in it Paſtors, Presbyters or Elders, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> Art. 31. <hi>We believe it is not lawful for any one to invade the government of the Church by his own Authority. We believe that this rule ought to be followed, that all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, Elders, and Deacons, ought to have a teſtimony of their calling, Matth.</hi> 28.10, 16. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>John</hi> 15.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7, 8. Art. 32. <hi>We believe that thoſe that are choſen Governours of any Church, ſhould take care amongſt themſelves, how the whole body may be moſt conveniently governed; yet ſo as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41764:8"/>they do not depart in any thing from the Inſtitution of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But this does not hinder, but that there may be a peculiar Inſtitution in all places as ſhall ſeem moſt convenient, Acts</hi> 14.23, 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 25.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> Confeſſion, Art. 31. <hi>We believe that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Elders, and Deacons, ought to be called to their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and promoted by the lawful election of the Church, with ſerious prayer to God for that purpoſe; and in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and manner which is preſcribed in the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bohemian</hi> Confeſſion, Art. 19. <hi>They teach that the Miniſters of the Church, to whom the Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments is committed, ought to be rightly inſtituted according to the Preſcription given by our Lord and his Apoſtles. — Wherefore prayer being made by the Elders, let them be confirmed in the Congregation to this work by the laying on of hands.</hi> And they refer to <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. to S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and then ſay, <hi>Wherefore no man is permitted to exerciſe the Office of a Prieſt amongſt us, but he that is called and inſtituted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe precepts, as it is meet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Canons of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Church ſpeak more fully in this matter, Can. 5. <hi>It pleaſeth that exact account ſhould be taken in Provincial Synods, and that ſuch order ſhould be appointed for the good of the Church, as neceſſity doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</hi> Can. 6. <hi>It ſhall be lawful for none to exerciſe the Miniſtry in private places or Hoſpitals, or any other place whatſoever, unleſs he be admitted according to the foregoing Canons, and he ſhall be ſubject to the Laws of the Church as well as any others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Canons ſay the ſame of Miniſters,<note place="margin">La diſciplin des Egliſe, &amp;c. par. Huiſſeau.</note> Can. 24. <hi>Miniſters ſhall not wander up and down, neither ſhall they have liberty to thruſt themſelves in by their own autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41764:9"/>where they pleaſe.</hi> Can. 26. <hi>A Miniſter that ſhall thruſt himſelf into a place, although he be approved by the people, cannot be approved by the neighbour Miniſters, or others; but ſhall be brought to the cogniſance of the Colloquy or Synod of the Province.</hi> Can. 57. <hi>Thoſe that ſhall thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Miniſtry, in Provinces and places where the pure Miniſtry is already eſtabliſhed, ſhall be ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to deſiſt; and in caſe they ſhall perſevere, they ſhall be declared Schiſmaticks, as alſo they that follow them, if they do not forſake them, after they have been admoniſhed of the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Aſſembly of Divines in their Confeſſion of Faith, Chap. 30. <hi>The Lord Jeſus as King and Head of his Church hath appointed a Government in the hand of Church-officers, diſtinct from the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi> Chap. 31. <hi>For the better Government and further Edification of the Church, there ought to be ſuch Aſſemblies as are commonly called Synods or Councils. — It belongeth to Synods and Councils miniſterially to determine Controverſies of Faith and Caſes of Conſcience, to ſet down Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for better ordering of the publick Worſhip of God, and Government of his Church, to receive Complaints in caſes of male Adminiſtration, and authoritatively to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſame;</hi> that is, by ſilencing thoſe that will not conform to them.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee what Order the Univerſal Church made in theſe matters,<note place="margin">Codex Can. Eccl. univerſal.</note> Can. 4. which is the renowned De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the firſt General Council held at <hi>Nice: A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ought to be appointed by all the Biſhops that are in the Province; but if this be difficult by reaſon of ſome urgent neceſſity, or becauſe of the length of the way, the Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be made by three at leaſt gathered together, and the reſt that are abſent approving what is done, and giving
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41764:9"/>their conſent by their Letters. And the Confirmation of all that is done in every Province muſt be by the Metropolitan.</hi> Can. 5. of the ſame Council; <hi>If any man be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, whether he be a Clergyman or a Layman, let this Sentence be obſerved by the Biſhops in every Province, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Canon, which does require, that thoſe that are rejected by one ſhould not be received by another. — And ſo they that have manifeſtly offended the Biſhop, ſhall be held juſtly excommunicated, till it ſhall ſeem good to the Company of Biſhops to decree a gentler Sentence.</hi> Can. 83. <hi>If any Biſhop that is depoſed by a Synod, or any Presbyter or Deacon that is depoſed by his Biſhop, ſhall offer to exerciſe any thing of his Miniſtry, whether he be a Biſhop, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtom going before, or a Prieſt, or a Deacon, he ſhall not have any hopes of being reſtored in a Synod, nor be permitted to make any Apologie for himſelf. And let all that joyn in Communion with him alſo be caſt out, eſpecially if they ſhall joyn with him after they know this Sentence is pronounced againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can. 84. <hi>If any Presbyter or Deacon ſhall deſpiſe his own Biſhop, and ſeparate himſelf from the Church, and hold a Congregation, and ſet up an Altar, and will not hearken to his Biſhop when he calls him, nor obey nor ſubmit to him when he calls him once and twice, let him be wholly depoſed, and that without remedy, and with utter incapacity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Honour again; but if he perſiſt to make diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and raiſe Schiſms in the Church, let him be reſtrained as a ſeditious perſon by the Secular Powers.</hi> Can. 91. <hi>If any Presbyter or Deacon depoſed by his own Biſhop, or any Biſhop depoſed by a Synod, ſhall offer to trouble the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ears, ſince he ought to apply himſelf to a greater Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, and refer the right which he thinks he has to more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and wait for their examination and judgment. But
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41764:10"/>if he ſhall deſpiſe them and trouble the King, he ſhall not be thought worthy of any pardon, nor have any place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or hopes of reſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can. 165. made at the ſecond General Council held at <hi>Conſtantinople; It is manifeſt that it appertains to the Synod of every Province, to order all matters within their Province, according as it is defined in the Council of Nice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that as the Law of Nature does require that there ſhould be an orderly way in all Societies, to determine all matters relating to the Government thereof; ſo Chriſt has appointed in his Church, that all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould obey their ſeveral Paſtors; and becauſe they are men like others, and die, he has appointed a way how their Offices ſhould be ſupplied to the end of the World; and for the more peaceable ordering of that matter has ſaid,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If any one refuſe to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an heathen man and a publican.</hi> And by his Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> And according to theſe Rules not onely the ancient and univerſal Church in all Ages, but even the Reformed Proteſtant Churches, to prevent Schiſms and Confuſions, have conſtantly decreed, that no man ought to exerciſe any Eccleſiaſtical Office in the Church, but with the allowance of each Provincial Synod, or according to ſuch Laws and Canons as they did preſcribe.<note place="margin">Independents, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, guilty of Schiſm.</note> And therefore all the Independents, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, that have no other outward Miſſion but the Choice of the People, and yet pretend to be Teachers and Governours of the Church, do like <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> that preſumed to burn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe without Gods warrant; and that Nation may expect Gods Judgments, that does permit ſuch Profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41764:10"/>of his Holy Name and Worſhip, and not take effectual care to hinder ſuch a notorious violation of the Prieſtly Office.</p>
               <p>But yet amongſt thoſe that maintain the neceſſity of an outward and orderly Miſſion, there are ſtill great Diſputes about the lawful Authority of thoſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Governours that charge men with Schiſm for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Obedience, and ſeparating themſelves from their Communion. Chriſt therefore having appointed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in his Church, muſt alſo have left ſome peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able way for ordaining and ſettling of every man in his Place and Office, ſo as to prevent Schiſms and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. And to that end the Apoſtle tells us,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſpirit of the Prophets</hi> (much more them of the Biſhops, &amp;c.) <hi>are ſubject to the Prophets;</hi> and our Lord has further ſaid, <hi>If any man refuſe to hear the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>let him be unto thee as an heathen man and a publican.</hi> According to theſe Rules of the Scripture the Chriſtian Church in all Ages did require, that Biſhops and Paſtors ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Provincial Synods of lawful Biſhops, or elſe according to ſuch Canons and Orders as were conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Provincial and Univerſal Councils of Biſhops. And this was the conſtant ſtanding Law of the Church for fifteen hundred years together, and in quiet times, it was conſtantly obſerved, either by open conſent or tacit approbation. But upon the Reformation the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and Apoſtolical Order of Epiſcopacy was not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſome places, but mere Presbyters did take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ordain other Presbyters, yet deſiring the reſtitution of the ancient Order of Biſhops if it might be, and ſtill maintaining that the ordaining Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſettling of all Affairs of the Church, ought to be done by the mutual conſent and appointment of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41764:11"/>the Eccleſiaſtical Governours, in their ſeveral Charges and Aſſemblies, as is largly to be ſeen by the Harmony of Confeſſions, and in ſeveral Canons that have been made by Reformed Churches about this matter. In pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this Order of Chriſt, and the Canons and Practice of the whole Church ancient and modern, Proteſtant <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi> our Biſhops and Clergy here in <hi>England</hi> are legally and rightly ordained and ſettled in their ſeveral Charges; and therefore to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey them, and ſeparate from their Communion, or to preſume publickly to exerciſe the Miniſterial Office againſt their command, is Schiſmatical, and contrary to the Order of Chriſt, and the whole Church of God. And all Popiſh Prieſts or Presbyterian Miniſters, or whoſoever they are that hold any Meetings and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations beſides the lawful Miniſters, and without their allowance, are formal Schiſmaticks, and ſo are all their Diſciples and Communicants. So that if there be any ſuch thing as Government in the Church, and any ſuch ſin as Schiſm, as I have ſhewed there are, the allowing men publickly to affront Gods Miniſters by Schiſmatical Congregations, and to live in open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their Authority, muſt needs bring great guilt and heavy Judgments upon the Nation.</p>
               <p>But againſt this it will be urged by the Papiſts, that our Biſhops are no lawful Biſhops, and our Clergy no lawful Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and authorized by the Pope.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer,<note place="margin">Papiſts guilty of Schiſm.</note> When they ſhall ſhew any Law or Tradition of the Univerſal Church, to make it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Pope to confirm our Biſhops, then I will allow the Objection to be of moment; but 'tis ſo far from that, that the Laws of the whole Church, and of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41764:11"/>many ancient Popes,<note place="margin">Conc. Nic. can. <hi>4.</hi> Conc. Ant. can. <hi>9.</hi> Vid. Diſt. <hi>64.</hi>
                  </note> do forbid the Pope to meddle with Ordinations in other Provinces, and expreſly ſay, that all Ordinations of Biſhops ought to be by the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans, and Biſhops of each reſpective Province amongſt themſelves. And ſo long as there is a peaceable agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt all our Biſhops and Clergy concerning this matter, that is a ſufficient reaſon to free us, and charge all Popiſh Prieſts here in <hi>England,</hi> and all their Adherents, with the guilt of Schiſm, and to make it appear that they do act contrary to the Law and Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the whole Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Presbyterians and Independents alſo,<note place="margin">Presbyterians and Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents guilty of Schiſm.</note> that had formerly Epiſcopal Ordination, or elſe Impoſition of Hands from Presbyters, which they eſteem ſufficient Holy Orders, are guilty of Schiſm, if they keep Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, or withdraw themſelves and others from the Obedience and Communion of the reſpective Biſhops and Miniſters of this Nation. For the Biſhops and Clergy being rightly conſtituted, and peaceably ſettled in their ſeveral Charges, according to the order of Chriſt, by undoubted Succeſſion from the Apoſtles, and according to the Canons and Tradition of the whole Church, and even after that manner by order of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Synods, which all Reformed Churches do practiſe and allow, they have Authority from the Holy Ghoſt, and do <hi>rule the Church over which the Holy Ghoſt has made them overſeers;</hi> and all in their Charges muſt <hi>obey them that have the rule over them, and ſubmit themſelves unto them, Heb.</hi> 13.17. Unleſs therefore they can prove, that the whole Church in all Ages was fundamentally miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in this matter, and that our Biſhops and Miniſters are no legal Paſtors of Chriſts Flock, they in diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them do diſobey Chriſt and the whole Church, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41764:12"/>are to be accounted as <hi>Heathens and Publicans.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> And then if our Land ſhould publickly permit, or not go about to take away ſuch publick Offences, we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that God ſhould pour down his indignation upon us as he did upon the Heathen, when we countenance thoſe that make themſelves as Heathens amongſt us. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Objections of Diſſenters anſwered.</head>
               <p>ALL that they can ſay in this matter is,<note place="margin">Object.</note> That the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> are lawful Church-governours over thoſe that chooſe and receive them, but over none elſe; and they having never choſen them for their Teachers and Governours, they are not ſo to them, and therefore they are no Schiſmaticks in withdrawing from their Communion, and chooſing other Governours for themſelves.</p>
               <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Anſw. People have no right to chooſe their Miniſters.</note> 'tis required that a Clergyman ſhould be of good behaviour, and have a good report of them which are without, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 7. And conſequently all Chriſtians have a right to except againſt ill manners, but I never find that Chriſt or his Apoſtles in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, or that any Word of God does allow, that the People ſhould have any thing to do in chooſing their Biſhops and Miniſters, much leſs had a Negative to reject whom they pleaſe. Indeed the Churches in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages have been moved with the nomination and earneſt inſtance of Kings and Princes, and by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41764:12"/>recommendation and petition of the People, to ordain ſuch men Biſhops and Prieſts as they did deſire, if they found them worthy; but 'tis by no Example or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, and they found ſo many inconveniences by it, that the Univerſal Church did forbid it, <hi>Concil. Laod. can.</hi> 13. reckoned among the Canons of the Univerſal Church; <hi>It ought not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the people to have the election of thoſe that are to be appointed to the ſacred Miniſtry.</hi> And therefore where Miniſters are peaceably ſettled according to the publick Order of the Church, the pretence of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Negative cannot free men from obedience, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their Schiſm in departing from them.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, all that right the People can pretend to, is transferred to their Repreſentatives in Parliament, who have in their Laws confirmed all the Biſhops and Clergy now in poſſeſſion by their Authority, and ſo they are ſettled by the Peoples conſent likewiſe; and therefore in all reſpects whatſoever our Clergy are undoubted Miniſters of Chriſt, and all within their charge muſt own them for ſuch, and ſubmit to their Authority.</p>
               <p>But the Parliament may alter theſe Laws, and give the People a Negative.</p>
               <p>I will not diſpute what they may or may not do in this matter, they having formerly made Laws to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thoſe Miniſters that are already, they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right from the Peoples conſent likewiſe, if that does avail any thing; and therefore as long as thoſe Miniſters live in the Orthodox Profeſſion of true Religion, they will be Schiſmaticks that diſobey them.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41764:13"/>
               <p>That there is an open flagrant Schiſm is plain, and the guilt of this muſt lie ſomewhere; it cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be charged upon the Biſhops and Clergy, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for they go on upon the ſame Rules and Methods that they did before 41, when there were few of theſe Nonconformiſts and ſeparate Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and according to the order of the whole Chriſtian Church; therefore the Crime muſt wholly lie upon thoſe who run away from their own Miniſters, and heap to themſelves Teachers and Diſciples, contrary to the Command of Chriſt and the Law of his Church.</p>
               <p>But they will ſay, They are not the Schiſmaticks, but the Biſhops and Clergy, by impoſing unlawful Ceremonies which they cannot ſubmit to, as the uſe of the Surplice, and an Aerial Croſs, and therefore muſt keep Coventicles of their own.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the Church was miſtaken in the impoſing theſe Ceremonies, what Authority can they have to keep Conventicles? Since they are but private men, a private Worſhip in their own Families is all that they can pretend to exerciſe; but that can be no War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for them to aſſemble in publick Congregations, and ſeduce others from their obedience to their lawful Teachers.</p>
               <p>As for the Ceremonies, they are no other than the whole Church of God in the purer times did obſerve and practiſe.</p>
               <p>For the Surplice S. <hi>Jerom</hi> upon <hi>Ezek.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Surplice</note> 42. ſays, <hi>The Divine Religion hath one habit in the Miniſtry, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in common uſe and converſation.</hi> And againſt the <hi>Pelagians, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>What offence, I ask, is it againſt God if I wear a more pure garment? If the Biſhop, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Deacon, and the reſt of the Eccleſiaſtical Order, do
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41764:13"/>go with a white garment when they adminiſter about holy things? Take heed, O ye Clergy; take heed, O ye that are devoted to an holy life: ye Widows and Virgins, you are in danger,</hi> (from theſe <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereticks) <hi>unleſs the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people do behold you in ſordid and in ragged Woollen Apparel.</hi> So that they were the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereticks that quarrelled againſt the uſe of the Surplice of old, for which S. <hi>Jerom</hi> does deride their folly and madneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concil.</hi> 4. <hi>Carthag. c.</hi> 41. 'tis decreed that <hi>A Deacon in the time of his oblation or reading onely ſhould wear a white garment.</hi> From whence we may very well conclude, that Biſhops and Prieſts likewiſe had a peculiar Habit in their ſacred Adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his Hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 23. does make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an holy Garment given by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to <hi>Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> the Biſhop, when he adorned the Church of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> that he ſhould wear it at the time of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of holy Baptiſm. And that this holy Garment being afterwards worn by a Stage-player, as he was dancing in it he fell down and died. Which inſtances do further prove there were uſed diſtinctive Habits in the Primitive Church in the time of the ſacred Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration.</p>
               <p>And for the uſe of the ſign of the Croſs Antiquity is much more full,<note place="margin">Of the ſign of the Croſs.</note> that one would wonder how men can neglect, much leſs blame a thing, which the godly Martyrs and ancient Fathers did ſo much uſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull. de Coron. Mil. c.</hi> 3. <hi>At every progreſs and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. we ſign our foreheads with the ſign of the Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Cyprian ep.</hi> 55. <hi>Let the forehead be fortified, that the ſign of God may be kept ſecure.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41764:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Jerom</hi> upon <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10. <hi>In the ancient Hebrew Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which the Samaritans uſe at this day, the letter Thau is of the figure of a Croſs, which is made in the forehead of Chriſtians, and often ſigned with the hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. tract.</hi> 11. <hi>in Joan. If we ſay to a Catechumen, Do you believe in Chriſt? He anſwers, I believe, and ſigns himſelf with the Croſs of Chriſt. He carries it in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and is not aſhamed of the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi> And in 118. <hi>Unleſs the ſign of the Croſs be applied, whether it be to the foreheads of the Believers, or to the water by which they are regenerated, or to the Sacrifice,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper) <hi>by which they are nouriſhed, none of them is rightly performed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 54. <hi>in Matth. All things amongſt us are performed with the ſign of the Croſs. If any be to be regenerated, that is baptized, the Croſs is uſed; if he be to be nouriſhed with myſtical food, if he be to be confirmed, and whatever elſe, every where the ſymbol of our victory is at hand. And for this cauſe we make the ſign of it with a great deal of care upon our houſes, and upon our walls, and upon our doors, upon our foreheads, and upon our minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were eaſie to bring many more inſtances of the primitive uſage of the Croſs, but theſe are ſufficient. But I will add ſome few Hiſtories to ſhew, how God himſelf did miraculouſly from Heaven encourage the Chriſtians in the uſe thereof. And the firſt ſhall be that renowned repreſentation of the Croſs in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens made to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> before his Army,<note place="margin">Vide Euſeb. in vita Conſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Socr. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> with this Inſcription joyned to it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>By this overcome;</hi> at which the Emperour and the whole Army were aſtoniſhed, and wondered what it ſhould mean. But while he doubted and reaſoned in his mind about it, be fell aſleep, and in his dream Chriſt ſeemed to appear to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41764:14"/>him with the ſign that was ſeen in the Heavens, and commanded him to make a repreſentation of the ſign that appeared to him, and to uſe it as a defence againſt the Conflicts of his Adverſaries; which when he awoke he declared to his Friends, and cauſed Croſſes to be made of Gold and precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> tells another remarkable ſtory of a miraculous appearing of a Croſs in the Heavens,<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. orat. <hi>2.</hi> adv. Jul.</note> in the days of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, who encouraged the <hi>Jews</hi> to rebuild their Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, which they did ſet about with all coſt and diligence, the very Women labouring amidſt the Dirt and Mortar. But there came an Earthquake and violent Storm, and Fire proceeded out of the Temple and conſumed ſome of them. <hi>Neither let any disbelieve this, but ſuch a one who may think upon the ſame reaſon to disbelieve other miracles of God. But what is yet more wonderful and illuſtrious, there ſtood a light in the heavens deſcribing the figure of a Croſs. And that figure and name which was before deſpiſed by wicked men in the earth, is now equally manifeſted unto all in heaven, and is made a trophy of Gods victory over the wicked, higher than all trophies— Theſe were the ſigns in heaven and in earth; but did not the air give forth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and was not that fanctified with the ſigns of Chriſts paſſion? Let them which were the ſpectators, and privy to theſe miracles, bring forth their garments marked with the ſign of the Croſs. For as ſoon as any of ours, or any ſtrangers did relate theſe things, or hear them related, preſently he ſaw this miracle on himſelf or him that ſtood by him, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had the figure of a Star upon him, or elſe he beheld it in the garments of another, exceeding the art of all Womens work, or moſt elaborate Embroidery. Which thing did ſo much amaze all the Beholders, that they all as it were with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41764:15"/>one voice at this ſign did call upon the God of the Chriſtians, and did endeavour with many praiſes and prayers to appeaſe his anger. And many making no longer delay, went preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Prieſts at the ſame time that this thing happened, and did uſe much ſupplication to be admitted into the Church, and to be made partakers of the more perfect diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and were ſanctified by holy Baptiſm. Socrates</hi> in his 3d. Book and 20th. Chapter does mention this ſame ſtory; and <hi>Melanchthon</hi> a ſober Proteſtant Writer does put it into his <hi>Chronicon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scultetus</hi> a grave Proteſtant Writer relates another Apparition of the Croſs in the Heavens,<note place="margin">Scultet. Annal. p. <hi>18.</hi> A. D. <hi>1517.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1517. <hi>Frederick Elector of Saxony, and John his brother, going to prayers on the Eve of the Nativity of our Lord with a great Attendance, ſee above the Tower in a ſerene Sky a ſhining purple Croſs, very great, and deſcribed with a clear Figure. The Spectators ſtand awhile amazed at the ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if God Almighty had been offended with the uſe of the Croſs, it cannot be thought he would have made ſuch miraculous repreſentations thereof in the Heavens, which muſt needs encourage the primitive Chriſtians in that cuſtom. Neither if there had been none of theſe repreſentations, can we think a thing ſo univerſally uſed in the purer Ages of the Church, ſhould be ſuperſtitious. For certainly ſome of thoſe holy Martyrs would have diſcovered the Error, and found out ſome means to have taken it away. And therefore the uſe of the Croſs can be no ſufficient ground to ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the People think we can pray better and preach better than the Conformiſts do,<note place="margin">See the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſign.</note> and find they edifie more under our inſtruction than by their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and therefore we may lawfully preach, and they lawfully hear us.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41764:15"/>
               <p>But the Apoſtle ſays,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves;</hi> but he does not ſay, Gad up and down, and hear and obey the beſt. So that if you ſhould teach them better, yet Edification does not conſiſt onely in Knowledge, but in Obedience alſo; and if you do inſtruct them in ſound knowledge, you muſt tell them they ought to hear their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and obey them and leave you; and therefore you muſt leave off to preach alſo. But what endleſs confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt this bring into the world, if Children ſhould refuſe to be inſtituted and yield obedience to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Servants to their Maſters, every conceited man to his reſpective Teachers and Governours, becauſe he fancies another man will teach and rule him better? And yet there will be as much reaſon for one as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; neither is there the leaſt colour for you to ſay, or the People to pretend, that your Prayers and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are more for edification, but the quite contrary, both for the Matter and Method.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Matter, all the ſubſtantial Truths in the opinion of all Churches, that are neceſſary to be known in order to Salvation, are taught in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and repeated, and ſome parts of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded upon every Lords Day; ſo that both old and young have their whole duty frequently reſounding in their ears. And our prayers are ſuch which they muſt needs confeſs are agreeable to Gods will, and therefore if devoutly offered up will certainly find acceptance at the Throne of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And then for the Method, the very Order of our Service, and the Returns of the Faſts and great Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals are a perpetual Catechiſm, and a conſtant motive to excite and quicken ſober Piety and true Devotion.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41764:16"/>
               <p>Whereas in the way of their teaching 'tis wholly left to the diſcretion of each Miniſter to teach what he will, and pray how he will; and what he does preach, and what he has prayed, neither he himſelf can tell, nor any of the people unleſs they could all write Short Hand, or had a Revelation from Heaven to inform them; neither can they be ſure in ſuch an <hi>ex tempore</hi> way, whether the Doctrine be ſound which he does teach, or the Prayers ſuch as are fit to be offered up unto God. Or ſuppoſe the Prayers and Preaching ſhould be according to Gods Word, yet may not the Miniſter eaſily through ignorance or forgetfulneſs neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to inſtruct the Congregation in many duties, and to offer up many prayers which are neceſſary to be done? What pretence then can there be for greater edification? The ſober Inſtruction that has been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and well approved of by the able men of the Nation, muſt certainly with judicious perſons be thought more tending to edification, than the <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> and private Conceptions of any ſingle man, and very often of young Students in Divinity. Their paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Exclamations, loud Noiſes, and affected Tones and Geſtures, may ſtir up mens Fancies, and make them Enthuſiaſtical; but the ſober inſtruction and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, and the well meditated prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> muſt make more knowing and ſerious Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>But how it comes about they cannot tell, yet they find they are more edified and better ſatisfied with the Nonconformiſts Preaching. As for their being ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that is no more than a <hi>Jew</hi> or a <hi>Turk,</hi> or any Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick will ſay, who do deceive their own Souls. And for their edification, that will be as groundleſs when it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41764:16"/>is look'd into, for they will be found defective in their Knowledge, and ſhort in their Obedience to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; ſo that it will appear to be nothing but a deluded Fancy and blind Zeal, which is much greater in Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and known Enthuſiaſts, and not the Fruit of the Spirit, which is Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance. True Edification does conſiſt in Love of God and our Neighbour, Humility, Mortification, and Self-denyal; and therefore the exerciſe of Faſting, ſolemnly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorating and meditating upon the bleſſed Examples of the Martyrs, caſting off all Pride, Self-love, and overweening their own Underſtandings; following the inſtruction, piety, and holy converſation of the primitive Fathers and Confeſſors, muſt needs be more effectual means to Edification, than the <hi>ex tempore</hi> and new-fangled Devices of modern Schiſmaticks, that ſet at naught the Wiſdom of all former Ages. Certainly they muſt wilfully ſhut their eyes, that cannot diſcover the vanity of ſuch wild pretences of Edification; as if the Church of God in all Ages were not better able to judge than theſe private men who oppoſe her Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as I plainly have demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>The laſt excuſe they generally make is, That they are Miniſters of Chriſt, and therefore neceſſity is laid upon them, and <hi>Wo be unto them if they preach not the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, be it ſo; but they muſt not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15.</note> be Buſie Bodies and Biſhops in another mans Charge. If they think there is ſuch a Duty lying upon them, they muſt go to ſome vacant places, and they will find enough amongſt the <hi>Indies;</hi> but there is no reaſon that they ſhould ſteal away other mens Flocks, and draw
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41764:17"/>people from the obedience of their lawful Governours. Beſides, being once Miniſters is not a reaſon ſufficient that they muſt always be allowed to exerciſe their Office; for there are ſome whoſe mouths muſt be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. and 'tis not for perſons that are cenſured to be Judges in their own caſe; there would be no peace in the world if a legal Sentence ſhould not take place, becauſe the party condemned ſhall ſay the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is unjuſt. So that all the Pleas they can make in their own defence do rather aggravate than excuſe their Schiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Ignorance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE next publick reigning ſin, that will bring Judgment upon our Nation, is Ignorance; which is a great ſcandal where there are ſo great means for to get knowledge, and ſo many men able and willing to inſtruct the ignorant and miſguided Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>I will not ſay but that many through careleſneſs may be wanting to themſelves; and perhaps the Teachers in ſome places have not been ſo induſtrious as they might have been; but the great cauſe of this Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is owing to our Schiſms and Diſtractions; for the Miniſters have been imployed in driving away Wolves, while they ſhould feed the Lambs; and to ſtrive with the obſtinate and perverſe, while they ſhould be catechiſing the weak and ignorant. And as the Miniſters have been hindered in inſtructing by theſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41764:17"/>Diviſions, ſo the people have taken occaſion to run away, and refuſe to hear their ſober information; and no wonder then if they continue in ignorance, and others will grow up efter them ſtill in the like want of knowledge and unbelief, and ſo will be indifferent to Popery, or any thing that is moſt for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>Now to ſuffer men to go on in this ignorance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking effectual care to bring them to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, muſt neceſſarily provoke Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt our Nation; neither can any remedy be found, but requiring the people both old and young diligently to attend the Publick Worſhip of God, and and Expoſition of the Catechiſm and Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſtrictly enjoyning the Miniſters to examine and inſtruct young Children in the ſame, whereby the old people alſo will by degrees come to underſtand their duty. And how can this ever be brought to paſs, but by taking away Conventicles, and compelling all Parents and Maſters to ſend their Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the Pariſh Churches? And becauſe ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes are ſo large and populous, that all the people can never receive inſtruction or ſerve God in one Church, care ought to be taken to divide ſuch Pariſhes, or to erect Chapels of Eaſe, that all Chriſtians may have room and opportunity to attend the Service of God without diſtraction. But while many are favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and winked at under the notion of having Tender Conſciences, and being ſober Proteſtants, and that they ſerve God in Conventicles, others that are lazy and careleſs will wholly neglect all kind of Religion, or thoughts about it. And as for thoſe that go to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles for better inſtruction, they are ſo far from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41764:18"/>finding it there, that moſt of the great Zealots are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the common Principles of Chriſtianity, and many of them are taught to deny weighty Truths, and to neglect and deſpiſe neceſſary Duties. Unleſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome more effectual care be taken to bring men to the knowledge of the Saving Truth, we muſt expect Gods heavy vengeance on our Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Profaneneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND now I come to the laſt publick ſin of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> open Profaneneſs, and againſt which our Hereticks and Schiſmaticks do much cry out, but yet have been the great means to breed and uphold it. This is an Epidemical Diſtemper, that has infected all ſorts of men, as well knowing as ignorant, Orthodox as Schiſmatical. When and how it ſprung up is eaſie for conſidering men to find out. All the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and onward till 41, it was a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that walked in darkneſs, and ſeldom durſt peep out to ſee the Sun; but ever ſince the Bonds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint have been let looſe, and the Laws taken away or relaxed in favour of Tender Conſciences, as was pretended, Atheiſm and Profaneneſs have come in like a floud upon us, and will certainly continue and increaſe till Conventicles be ſuppreſſed, and men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to hear ſober inſtruction, and frequent the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip of God. For there is a natural ſelf-love in the beſt of men, which will encline them to eaſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41764:18"/>and pleaſure, and that meeting with no check without, and having all the Incentives from the Devil within, will unavoidably blind the Underſtanding, and lead the Will captive to all wickedneſs, unleſs the efficacy of Gods Grace does ſtrongly incline and aſſiſt them to overcome ſuch Motions. But ſuch effectual Grace is not to be found but in the Church, and in the uſe of ſuch means as the Goſpel does direct us unto.</p>
               <p>Theſe are not in Conventicles, or in Taverns, or at home by the Fire ſide in Private Houſes, at the time of Gods Publick Worſhip; but in the Unity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church. <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20. But that is according to his will and command, and not in Schiſm and Diſobedience to their lawful Governours and Inſtructors.</p>
               <p>Gods Grace alone upon many tempers without pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment will not work a Reformation, much leſs pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments alone without the aſſiſtance of Gods Grace; therefore God has appointed both, and authorized Men to be inſtruments to apply them. The Miniſters have power to diſpenſe the Word and Sacraments, and with them the Graces of God, to thoſe that devoutly receive them; but they cannot compell any to attend upon the means. The Magiſtrates they can compell men to attend upon the means, but they cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe the Graces of Gods Spirit; therefore both muſt concur, and all little enough to cure the Profaneneſs of the Age. What influence puniſhment has we may learn from Gods Word, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Withhold not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the child,</hi> (and many profane men are worſe than Children) <hi>for thou ſhalt beat him with the rod, and deliver his ſoul from hell.</hi> And God ſays,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>In their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41764:19"/>they will ſeek me early.</hi> And therefore when Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours neglect their duty, he takes the chaſtiſement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.32. <hi>If they break my ſtatutes, and keep not my commandments, I will viſit their offences with a rod, and their ſin with ſcourges.</hi> And what effect his Viſitation has we learn from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.34. <hi>When he ſlew them they ſought him, and turned them early and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after God.</hi> As yet God does but ſhake his rod over the Land, and we hear of nothing but Plots, and the deſtroying Angel does not execute Gods Judgment againſt it, but gives this fair warning, and ſeaſonable opportunity for Governours, who are to de <hi>a terror to evil doers, Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. to reform theſe evils by their diſcipline and correction; but if they do not uſe their power to reſtrain men from theſe licentious provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I fear theſe threatnings are the forerunners of Gods own dreadful execution upon us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Conventicles the great means to bring in Popery.</head>
               <p>I Know it will be replied by ſome, theſe are very great Evils, and ought to be remedied in due time; but we cannot do all things at once; we are now find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ways to exclude Popery, and to propoſe other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters would be thought a deſign wholly to hinder all effectual care to prevent our danger from the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>This I confeſs is often urged to put off all Debates about redreſſing theſe crying ſins of the Nation; but I ſee no reaſon in it, but the quite contrary, for it is the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41764:19"/>onely means to keep out Popery, and without it all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours will come to nothing. And this is made as evident as the Sun at Noon-day; for what do the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts labour after, or deſire more, but to keep up theſe Diviſions? Who are more for a Toleration than they, though they themſelves have no benefit by it in their own perſons? Did not Father <hi>Cummin</hi> a known Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt firſt ſet afoot theſe Diſſentions in <hi>England,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward was rewarded at <hi>Rome</hi> for the Service he had done that Court by it? And have they not in all Ages preached in Conventicles, and by their Learning and Cunning kept them up? Does not the firſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer of the Plot inform the World upon Oath,<note place="margin">See a Diſcourſe called Foxes and Firebrands.</note>that there were Popiſh Prieſts ſent into <hi>Scotland</hi> to preach amongſt the Field Conventicles? And is it not a known thing, that Father <hi>Brown</hi> and the Lord <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (undoubted Papiſts) were thought great Zealots amongſt the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Rebels? And 'tis as certain that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Whitebread</hi> often preached about in Conventicles in <hi>England.</hi> And while they thus herd together, one can never be ſuppreſſed while the other is tolerated. And for a Teſt with Oaths to diſtinguiſh them, that will never do, much leſs a Teſt without an Oath; for a Teſt being but one tranſient act to ſecure their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates, men of deſign will readily leap over ſuch an offence, and find an eaſie Abſolution when 'tis for the good of the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But why do the Papiſts thus joyn with and uphold theſe Conventicles? Do they think favourably of their Opinions, or count them better Chriſtians than others? No, nothing leſs; but by that means they take men off from all ſettled Principles, and lead them into confuſion, and then they find they are eaſily
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41764:20"/>baffled out of their Profeſſion, and wrought upon to come over to them. So that to tolerate Diſſenters, and keep up theſe Diviſions, is to do the Papiſts work for them whileſt they are aſleep, and with one hand to hold them up, while with the other you go to pull them down.</p>
               <p>But if Conventicles be taken away, and all people old and young be inſtructed in the ſober Principles of the ſound Religion that is taught in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> theſe Popiſh deſigns of unſettling people will be fruſtrated, and they muſt neceſſarily fall with other Diſſenters. So that in the way of Policy as well as Religion, the onely means to keep out Popery is by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away theſe open Schiſms, and ſettling the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip of God in beauty and order. And this has been hitherto thought the Wiſdom of the Nation, and eſpecially in the times of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when that Policy had the bleſſing of Honour abroad and Peace at home.</p>
               <p>But perhaps ſome may hope by force to keep out Popery, and theſe Diſſenters will joyn with them to do it. But are they ſtronger than God, and can they withſtand his vengeance? If theſe ſins are ſo heinous as to draw down Gods indignation, he can eaſily bring to nought all ſuch devices.</p>
               <p>And yet further, when men act upon Maxims of Policy contrary to the Rules of Religion, how many ways are they defeated in their aim? Beſides, when theſe Diſſenters build upon no ſettled Principles, their Humours change, their Intereſts vary; and ſo may Miniſters of State be altered, and the Government put on another face, and then cunning is beyond force, and the ſtream of the Multitude will be carried another
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41764:20"/>way, and that Torrent which now runs againſt, may be imployed for the Papiſts. Of this we have an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al inſtance in the <hi>Jews</hi> dealing with our Saviour; for they that led him in triumph crying, <hi>Hoſanna, bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord;</hi> quickly changed their Acclamations into, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him.</hi> And there are too many examples of profane ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, rolling from Presbyterians to Independents, then to Anabaptiſts, afterward to Quakers, and at length to Papiſts; and many times when the former Devil is gone out, ſeven worſe enter in.</p>
               <p>Therefore you my Lords and Gentlemen have taken another courſe, you do not truſt to human ſtrength, or rely upon worldly policy, but by prayer and faſting humbly fly to and implore the Divine Aſſiſtance. You muſt not then neglect ordinary means and expect Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; or hope that God ſhould remove his judgments, till effectual care be taken to reform theſe crying ſins.</p>
               <p>I fear Popery, and with an amazing horror dread the ſpiritual and temporal miſchiefs thereof; but unleſs theſe ſins be reformed, I fear alſo that is a ſcourge God has provided for this Nation. Therefore as you have faſted and prayed, ſo to make them prevail for mercy you muſt <hi>looſe the bands of wickedneſs, Iſa.</hi> 58.6. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from before Gods eyes: ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well. If ye be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the land: but if ye refuſe and rebell, ye ſhall be devoured with the ſword. Iſ a.</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41764:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Comprehenſion the certain way to greater Diviſion.</head>
               <p>HAving ſeen the Cauſes of our Diſtractions, we are to inquire after the means of an Happy Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which all ought to wiſh and pray for; yet how to expect it I do not ſee, but by requiring ſtrict Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now eſtabliſhed, wherein ten thouſand Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and moſt of the Nobility and Gentry are agreed. For the Independents, Anabaptiſts, and Quakers deſire no Union with us, neither will their Principles admit any unleſs the Church will perfectly go over to them, which can never be done. As for the Presbyterians, they never did nor never will like the Common Prayer, as long as they can be flattered by Enthuſiaſtick Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in Conventicles, though they can and often do joyn with it after their careleſs manner. So that all the Union that can be hoped for by changing of the preſent Laws of Subſcription, Declaration, and the like, will be to bring in forty or fifty of theſe Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick Preachers into the Church, and then beſides the Schiſms without amongſt the Fanaticks, they will breed a Diviſion alſo within the Church, amongſt thoſe that will call themſelves the Conformable Clergy; for their Enthuſiaſtical way will be onely admired by the Vulgar, and all the ſober judicious Divines will be ſlighted as unprofitable Preachers.</p>
               <p>Beſides, having ſtood out twenty years in defiance of all Subſcriptions and Declarations, to teſtifie their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Common Prayer, and willingneſs to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41764:21"/>uphold the Government in Church and State as it is now eſtabliſhed, they will upon the taking away theſe Obligations, not onely think themſelves at liberty, but bound in honour and duty to endeavour the extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both; at beſt will keep men up and further them in contempt of the publick Prayers and Orders of the Church, and ſo ſpoil all ſerious Devotion.</p>
               <p>That neglect and contempt they have brought alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon the publick Prayers and Sacraments, has been no ſmall profanation of Gods Name, and the great ground of all other Profaneneſs; ſo that if they gain this point, to be taken into the Church upon their own terms, after they have caſt ſuch contempt upon it, they can readily then tell the people what good effect their reſolution and clamours have had, and encourage them to perſiſt in their demands; and there is no doubt but they ſhall be able to take the whole Conſtitution of the Church away. And if they cannot effect that, yet what a miſerable caſe will it be, when the publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Sacraments, Faſts and Feaſts, ſhall be thought by theſe that will call themſelves the Godly Party, the Miſery and Grievance of the Nation. Thoſe that dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee and hear how Gods publick Worſhip is contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Party, cannot but with bleeding hearts and ſorrowful groans, lament for the ſad condition of the Nation, and fear greater evils yet from that they call <hi>Comprehenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe matters muſt be left to your Wiſdom to conſider of, and in all former Ages it was the cuſtom to adviſe with the Biſhops and Clergy in their Synods about ſettling Religion. Thus did the pious <hi>Roman Caeſars</hi> in their times, and our Kings and Parliaments hitherto, and we cannot doubt the like from you, who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41764:22"/>by faſting and prayer do ſeek to God for direction. However this muſt never be forgotten, when we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after a Union, we muſt not ſeparate from the whole Church of God, nor hope to keep out Popery by upholding Ignorance and Profaneneſs. But if ever we expect Gods bleſſing and an Happy Union, it muſt be by ſettling ſound Religion and true Piety in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for while Hereſie and Schiſm, Ignorance and Profaneneſs, are ſuffered without controul, we muſt look for Plots and Conſpiracies, Miſeries and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to attend us.</p>
               <p>Having therefore ſhewed by plain matter of fact, from the Confeſſions of Proteſtant Churches, and alſo by the Tradition and Decrees of the Catholick Church, that the Quakers and Anabaptiſts do teach manifeſt and condemned Hereſie; and that the Papiſts, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and Independents that keep Conventicles, are undoubted Schiſmaticks; and that Hereſie and Schiſm are heinous offences in the ſight of God; the firſt ſtep to publick Reformation and a Happy Union is, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to take away all their Conventicles, and at leaſt make them all reſt ſatisfied with a private Worſhip in their own Families.</p>
               <p>And becauſe under their ſhelter abundance of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and profane perſons have grown up amongſt us, at the ſame time the utmoſt endeavour muſt be uſed to compell all the ignorant ſort at leaſt to hear ſober In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and by ſevere penalties to reſtrain Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Vice and Wickedneſs. And if theſe things be carefully provided againſt, as far as is poſſible by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority, men that are not reformed by ſuch means ſhall periſh for their own ſins, but God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41764:22"/>our humiliation, and hearken unto our prayers, and not onely deliver our Nation from the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Popery, but from all other publick evils and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities.</p>
               <p>But if Quakers and Anabaptiſts be ſtill permitted to propagate their Hereſies, and Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents to uphold their Schiſmatical Conventicles, Papiſts will lurk among them, Ignorance and Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will more and more increaſe, and ſo God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his diſpleaſure, and be more provoked againſt us; and what can we expect then from an angry God and a ſinful People, but Popery, Miſery, and Deſolation!</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41764:23"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>SInce the writing of theſe Papers the Reverend and Learned Dean of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> has publiſhed a great and elaborate Book, where he does largly prove and further confirm what I could but briefly mention in this ſhort Inquiry; and in pag. 45. he ſays,<note place="margin">Pref. p. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>My judgment being, that a cauſleſs breaking the peace of the Church we live in, is really as great and as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a ſin as Murder, and in ſome reſpects aggravated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it. And herein having the concurrence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the greateſt reputation both ancient and modern. Would they have me repreſent that as no ſin which I think to be ſo great a one, or thoſe as not guilty whom in my conſcience I thought to be guilty of it? Would they have had me ſuffered this ſin to have lain upon them, and not reproved it? Would they have had me found all the ſoft and palliating conſiderations to have leſſened their ſenſe of it? No, I had ſeen too much of this already, and a mighty prejudice done thereby to men otherwiſe ſcrupulous and conſcientious, that ſeem to have loſt all ſenſe of this ſin.</hi> And then after he had more ſeriouſly weighed and examined all their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to juſtifie themſelves from this Guilt, he concludes his Book thus; <hi>Although I make no ſuch Appeals to the Day of Judgment as others do, yet I cannot but declare to the world, as one that believes a Judgment to come, that upon the moſt diligent ſearch and careful inquiry into this matter, I cannot find any plea ſufficient to juſtifie in point of conſcience the preſent Separation from the Church of England.</hi> If there be no ſufficient plea to juſtifie the Separation, then theſe that by their Separation break
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41764:23"/>the peace of our Church, are guilty of a ſin as great and dangerous as Murder, in the opinion of this Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Perſon. And thence we may conclude, it will cry aloud for vengeance in the ears of God as Bloud doth. But the Learned Dean out of his abundant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Union, and Compaſſion towards Diſſenters, does make ſome Propoſals of Accommodation with the ſobereſt of them. The particulars are many, and not to be conſidered in this ſhort Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>In general therefore I do readily agree with the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> that the uſe of the Sacraments in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church ought to be moſt free from all exceptions, and they ought to be ſo adminiſtred, as rather to invite than diſcourage ſcrupulous perſons from joyning in them; and therefore I would have nothing made as a Condition of Communion, but what was moſt clear and undoubted in the practice of the Ancient and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, or evidently deduced from the Word of God, and generally held lawful by the greateſt part of ſober Divines in all Ages.</p>
            <p>But I do not ſee we can agree to the taking away of the ancient Conſtitutions and Ceremonies of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Catholick Church, without great ſcandal to many ſober Chriſtians, and weakning of out cauſe, and giving great advantage to the Adverſaries of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which the Reverend Dean does very excellently ſet forth pag. 4. of his Preface; <hi>It is of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſequeuce for preventing the return of Popery, that men rightly underſtand what it is. For when they are as much afraid of an innocent Ceremony, as of real Idolatry, and think they can worſhip Images, and adore the Hoſt, on the ſame grounds that they may uſe the ſign of the Croſs, or kneel at the Communion; when they are brought to ſee their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41764:24"/>miſtake in one caſe, they will ſuſpect themſelves deceived in the other alſo. For they who took that to be Popery which is not, will be apt to think Popery it ſelf is not ſo bad as it was repreſented; and ſo from want of right underſtanding the differences between us, may be eaſily carried from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme to another. For when they find the undoubted practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ancient Church condemned as Popiſh and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian by their Teachers, they muſt conclude Popery to be of much greater Antiquity than really it is; and when they can trace it ſo very near the Apoſtles times, they will ſoon believe it ſettled by the Apoſtles themſelves. For it will be very hard to perſuade any conſidering men, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church ſhould degenerate ſo ſoon, ſo unanimouſly, ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, as it muſt do if Epiſcopal Government, and the uſe of ſome ſignificant Ceremonies, were any parts of that Apoſtacy— Which is a matter ſo incredible, that thoſe who can believe ſuch a part of Popery could prevail ſo ſoon in the Chriſtian Church, may be brought to believe that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others did. So mighty a prejudice do the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our Churches enemies bring upon the Cauſe of the Reformation. And thoſe who forgo the teſtimony of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, as all the Oppoſers of the Church of England muſt do, muſt unavoidably run into inſuperable difficulties in dealing with the Papiſts, which the Principles of our Church do lead us through. For we can juſtly charge Popery as an unreaſonable innovation, when we allow the undoubted Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices and Government of the ancient Church for many ages after Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſe of the Croſs and Surplice, and other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church, being then of undoubted Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Chriſtian Church, to take them away to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie our Diſſenters, who count them Popiſh and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, is to undervalue the Piety of the primitive
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41764:24"/>Fathers, and will expoſe us to the juſt reproaches of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and harden the Diſſenters in their former belief. Whereas if the Teſtimony of Antiquity be of ſo great moment to uphold the Authority of our Church, we ought rather to be immovable in adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ancient Cuſtoms, that we may teach the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that 'tis Novelty not Antiquity that we reject in them, and to root out of the minds of the Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that fooliſh perſuaſion that ſignficant Ceremonies are ſuperſtitious; which can never be done otherwiſe than by ſhewing, that they muſt condemn the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church in the pureſt Ages upon the ſame account, and expoſe our Religion to the extravagant Fancies of every conceited Humoriſt, and ſo drive away many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men from our Communion. To keep up then the Reverence of Antiquity, and preſerve the Honour of the Reformation, we muſt not take away the uſe of the Croſs and Surplice, and other Orders of our Church, which are of ſuch undoubted Antiquity and univerſal practice in the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>And as for Toleration, the ſame Reverend Author does ſay, pag. 79. <hi>It will be found impoſſible to root out Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery where Toleration is allowed;</hi> which he does there ſhew with demonſtrative reaſons. But becauſe ſome are apt to think a limited Toleration of ſome ſort of men may be granted without any harm. It is to be conſidered, Firſt, if Schiſm be ſuch a grievous crime, as to be as great and dangerous as Murder, how can Toleration be granted to ſo great a ſin, without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the guilt of the Bloud of Souls upon our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Secondly, if Schiſm be a ſin of ſo heinous a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what a dangerous thing will it be to lay ſuch a ſtumbling block before the common people, as to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41764:25"/>grant a Toleration of thoſe Preachers who are Maſters of Inſinuation, to ſeduce the weak and ignorant into ſuch a deſtructive Separation? Therefore when all is done, the onely probable way of an Happy Union, is by ſetting aſide all thoughts of Toleration or Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, upon any other Principles than the Word of God, as it has been interpreted by the Rules and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the Ancient and Catholick Church, and in them all ſober Proteſtants and devout Chriſtians, when they come to underſtand them will readily agree.</p>
            <p>For this was the principle upon which <hi>Luther</hi> and the Proteſtants in <hi>Germany</hi> began the Reformation; witneſs the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Confeſſion, chap. 21. <hi>We do not deſpiſe the conſent of the Catholick Church, neither is it our intention to bring into the Church any new Opinion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Holy Church; neither will we patronize any wicked or ſeditious Opinions which the Catholick Church has condemned. For we were not led to embrace this Doctrine by any evil concupiſcence, but compelled to it by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Word of God, and of the ancient Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what theſe Rules are concerning our preſent Circumſtances, the foregoing Diſcourſe will clearly ſhew; but will more fully appear in my former Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of <hi>The Original of all Plots in Chriſtendom,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have not onely demonſtrated, that the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> condemned in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have no foundation in the Law and Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Catholick Church, and many of them are againſt both; and anſwered the Objections made by the Author of <hi>The Guide in Controverſie,</hi> and other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts againſt our Reformation; but alſo proved that the Doctrine and Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:41764:25"/>as it is now eſtabliſhed, are according to the Laws and Tradition of the Ancient and Catholick Church, and approved of by the greateſt part of all Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in all Ages, and even at this very day; to which Treatiſe I refer the Reader for further ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>So that when we have a truly Orthodox Religion generally approved of in all Ages eſtabliſhed amongſt us, and ten thouſand Clergymen, many of them men of as great Piety and Learning as ever were in any Age to propagate and uphold it, if Conventicles, which diſtract the Common People, were effectually taken away, the Body of the Nation would quickly embrace it, and ſo we ſhould ſee an Happy Union, and that would procure the bleſſing of God, and for ever keep out Popery from ſettling in our Nation.</p>
            <p>And ſince Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> and the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> did both confeſs before their death, that their Church did hope to bring in Popery by Toleration and keeping up Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, ſurely we ought in all reaſon to conclude the taking them away muſt be the readieſt means to keep it out.</p>
            <p>Thus as a Divine and hearty Welwiſher to the peace and happineſs of my Native Countrey, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to lay open the Cauſes and Remedies of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, though with the utmoſt peril of my Life or Welbeing, whether I reſpect the Papiſts or other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters. Had I therefore either conſulted my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage or my ſafety, I had better have ſpared my pains, than thus to have provoked their hatred againſt me; but I thank God I had other Motives to perſuade me, than any temporal Concerns of my own, for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, the Peace of his Church, and the preſent and eternal Welfare of ſo many thouſand Souls do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41764:26"/>upon the right Settlement of Religion, which is the thing I now propoſe, not out of my own Fancy, or upon any private models and conjectures, but upon that ſure immovable foundation of the Ancient and <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in all ages, which will quiet the minds of all ſober people, take a way thoſe heats and animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are ſtirred up amongſt Chriſtians, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecure our Nation from deſtruction.</p>
            <p>I know this will be thought a vain Aſſertion by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but with all ſerious perſons that mind Religion it is an undoubted truth, that the onely way to obtain peace and quietneſs, is by religious performing of our duty to God; and ſince there are ſo many pretenders to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that go about to devour and deſtroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till there be found ſome way to undeceive theſe erroneous Pretenders, not onely Gods commands, but the peace of Chriſtendom will be little regarded, and conſequently we muſt lie expoſed to perpetual Wars and Maſſacres.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe Diviſions are kept up upon the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the great Sanctity and Authority of their ſeveral Upholders; unleſs therefore we can urge their Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with a greater Authority, and more undoubted Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Holineſs than they lay claim to, we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hope to undeceive them. And theſe will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly appear in that way which I defend the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for what Authority can be greater than the Church of God in all ages, in oppoſition to a particular Church, or a few private perſons? Or who can give better evidence of their Holineſs than the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>dele</hi> in. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> c. 27. <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>l.</hi> 33. <hi>after</hi> figure <hi>adde</hi> as.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41764:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
